Ed Michaels Papers
Ed Michaels Papers
1962-1989
Michaels, Ed.
1 linear ft.
Collection contains papers, reports and newspaper articles on resin transfer molding, including the renovation of the Truman balcony at the White House; photographs and slides from Michaels' career and the products he created; and videotapes.
2651140
Biographical History
Ed Michaels (1922-2002) was an American inventor and manufacturer in the plastics industry.
Michaels worked with reinforced thermoset plastics and developed zero-shrink polyester resin formulations used in molds for composites, making it possible to mold large parts with light-weight polyester molds. He obtained several patents related to the Resin Transfer Mold Process (RTM). Over the course of his career he formed two companies: Composites Consulting in Sheboygan Falls, WI and Fiberglass, Tooling and Specialties. He used his skills to renovate the White House Truman Balcony using polyester. He died March 26, 2002.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Ed Michaels Papers contains papers, reports and newspaper articles on resin transfer molding, including the renovation of the Truman balcony at the White House; images (photographs and slides) from Michaels' career and the products he created; and videotapes.
Arrangement of the Collection
Collection was already processed upon receipt by. Notes below were provided with the collection.
Collection found in no order except the Polaroids which were arranged in two binders, titled Fiberglass Tooling RTM and Repair Rebuilding, and the slides. Slides are labeled and in order as left by Michaels. Arranged in series by format. Polaroids are filed in the order in which they were in the binders. [Processed 2006 by Margaret O. Moore, Donohue Group, Inc., Wethersfield, CT.]
Related Material
has numerous holdings in the areas of plastics and industrial design. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Business and Industry; Plastics; Michaels, Ed.; Glass fibers.; Gums and resins, Synthetic.; Plastics industry and trade.; Plastics -- Molds.; Automobiles -- Parts.; Molding materials.; Beta (Betamax); Clippings (information artifacts); Hi-8.; Photographs.; Slides (photographs); Reports.; VHS.; Videocassettes.; Inventors.; Manufacturers.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Transfer from National Plastics Center and Museum, 11/06/2008. Originally, gift of Mrs. Esther Michaels via Thomas E. Doyle.
Inventory
- Papers, reports, and articles
  - Miscellaneous, newspaper clippings, including on the Truman balcony renovation at the White House, and papers on resin transfer molding, FRP Manufacturing (Kohler, Inc.) and polyester technology (Koppers) (Box 1)
- Photographs, 1962-1989
  - Prints, 387 items
    - Fiberglass plant, series A (Box 3)
    - Fiberglass plant, series B (Box 3)
    - Fiberglass production (Box 3)
    - "Fiberglass Tooling RTM" binder (Box 2)
    - Michaels in his office (Box 3)
    - "Repair Rebuilding" binder (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous, 8 items; Banning High School, Ed Michaels with unidentified man, and workers handling plastic pieces (Box 1)
  - Slides, 1198 items
    - Bway Elixir doors/Alta Manufacturing, c. 1962-1984 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Toledo Plant, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Trips, 1970-1972 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - SPI, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Fritz boat, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - RTM - molding, Plastark (?), 1983 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - White House gutter & fascia, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - SPI, Houston, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Guard doors, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - RTM (has identifying list), c. 1984-1987 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - RTM, misc. (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Assembly of doors, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Raising/lowering device, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Plenco machine, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Artificial limb, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Macair, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Wet jet, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Van (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Air shroud, Envirex (?), Macair (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Mack Truck (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Wind blade, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Helix I, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - RTM (has identifying list), 1987-1988 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Back of house & garden, EEA, Oshkosk river trip, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - RTM (has identifying list), 1988-1989 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Misc. raise/lowering device, 1988-1989 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Unidentified, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - "Fiberglass tool", 18 packets of 14-18 slides each (Box 5)
    - "Transmold", 10 packets of 14-18 slides each (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous, companies represented include DuPont, Kawasaki, W.H. Brady, Yakima; may also include some personal slides; 20 packets of 14-18 slides each (Box 5)
- Videotapes
  - 1A Resin Transfer Mold (RTM) at Heicom, michaels_e_002; Birth of A new CO. 57m 45A, Fluidization bed, MRI for knee, cheese press lid. By N. Ed Michaels, Composites Consulting; VHS; running time 120:00 (Box 6)
  - Cheese Press Lid; Fluidization Bed; MRI No. 2A; Wind Blade, michaels_e_006; 8 mm Hi8 Video; running time 20:00 (Box 6)
  - Composites Consulting, Resin Transfer Mold (RTM) No. 1, michaels_e_001; Formerly Fiberglass Tooling and Specialties, Inc. N. Ed Michaels.; VHS; running time 120:00 (Box 6)
  - Hauff Wind Blade (1st Edit), michaels_e_003; VHS; running time 120:00 (Box 6)
  - Resin Transfer Mold (RTM), michaels_e_005; Betamax (Box 6)
  - Training Hand Lay Up in Puebla; Working on Bus Seats (Copy), michaels_e_004; VHS (Box 6)